<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>she blogs</title>
    <atom:link href="http://now.she.codes/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link>
    <link>http://now.she.codes/blog</link>
    <description>she.codes' official blog</description>
    <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
    <generator>Wintersmith - https://github.com/jnordberg/wintersmith</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <item>
      <title>she.coders get exclusive tickets for JSConfEU 2014!</title>
      <link>http://now.she.codes/blog/articles/JSConfEU-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://now.she.codes/blog/articles/JSConfEU-2014/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;JavaScript is an exteremly versatile language and our language of choice when it comes to teaching programming. Euorpe’s JavaScript enthusiasts meet each year at JSConfEU in Berlin. It is the best event on the continent to learn about new developments and to celebrate  great parties with the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;JSConfEU’s organizers always have been very commited to work towards better gender parity among speakers at their events. Due to its vast popularity, conference tickets are being sold out within minites after releasing a new block. This unfortunately works against diversity among attendees. This year JSConfEU asked she.codes to help with making more tickets available to women and assigned us an exclusive block of tickets!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on École 42</title>
      <link>http://now.she.codes/blog/articles/ecole-42/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2014 02:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="true">http://now.she.codes/blog/articles/ecole-42/</guid>
      <author></author>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;a href=&quot;http://venturebeat.com/2014/06/13/this-french-tech-school-has-no-teachers-no-books-no-tuition-and-it-could-change-everything/&quot;&gt;an interesting article&lt;/a&gt; about École 42. It may be a bit silly to compare this 70 million euro venture to our teeny weeny organisation, but I like to do silly things at times. There are a lot of similarities between their approach and what we plan to do at &lt;a href=&quot;http://she.codes/&quot;&gt;she.codes&lt;/a&gt;, and some key differences.
&lt;span class=&quot;more&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; There are no teachers. Instead of transfering knowledge from one person to a group of pupils, the sutends use the Internet and their peers. Knowledge flows in all directions. Groups of students work on projects together and gather hands-on experience in what it is like to deliver a product. Both approaches emphasise collaboration and peer support. We share the funding model too: both schools count on donations as a primary source of funding. Both schools are free for students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, there is one important difference: École 42 is located in a physical building, and their students are being equiped with hardware and live and learn on campus. Therefor the number of students they can accept is limited. Because of thr huge demand, École 42’s acceptace rate is even lower than rates of elite universities like Harvard or Srandford and applicants have to pass hardcore tests in order to be accepted. As a consequence, only students that already have a strong backround in computing make it into École 42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At she.codes however, our mission is to bring as many women into the software industry as we can, including those with little or no prior exposure to ptogramming. Because we do not have physical restrictions, we will be able to accept any number of students. Our platform’s matchmaking feature seleccts students with similar skill levels for a remote pair programming session. The larger the pool of student is, the better this will work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt; Nicolas Sadirac, École 42’s director, mentions that prestigious universities already expressed interest in the school’s  approach. But what will they provide in this project-driven, teacherless peer-to-peer learning scenario? I can’t think of much more than the class room. The fact that many of today’s most successful software developers do not have academic degrees  shows that universities fail to deliver what the industry demands for quite a while now. Classrooms? Not sure if we need them at all!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>